[MUSIC PLAYING] https://youtu.be/CKDylrcrYqE
[MUSIC PLAYING] https://youtu.be/CKDylrcrYqE
K. MICHAEL HAYS: Architecture, from its very beginning, has been made of stone, and when it hasn't been
K. MICHAEL HAYS: Ngay từ khi bắt đầu, kiến trúc đã được làm từ đá, và khi
made of stone, it's been made to look like it's made of stone.
nó không được làm từ đá thì cũng trông giống như được làm từ đá
Windows may have glass in them, but windows in a stone wall are simply openings.
Các cửa sổ có thể có kính nhưng những chiếc cửa số trên tường đá chỉ đơn giản để mở
The glass itself is not important.
Kính không hề quan trọng
The development of technologies that allow the production of large sheets of glass and
Sự phát triển của công nghệ cho phép việc sản xuất các tấm kính lớn và
the materials with tensile strength, like steel, had the power to enormously change
vật liệu với cường độ chịu kéo như thép, có khả năng thay đổi lớn
the way buildings are made.
cách xây dựng các tòa nhà
But how would that necessarily affect architecture?
Tuy nhiên, điều đó ảnh hướng tất yếu tới kiến trúc như thế nào
How would that change architecture's
thay đổi chức năng tiêu biểu của kiến
representational function?
như thế nào?
How would that change architecture as the art of building?
và thay đổi kiến trúc nghệ thuật xây dựng ra sao?
The advances in modern technology and the invention of new materials
Những tiến bộ trong công nghệ hiện đại và việc phát minh những vật liệu mới
were not an inevitable helpful contributor to the goals of architecture culture.
không phải là những đóng góp hữu ích quen thuộc đối với mục tiêu của văn hóa kiến trúc.
How can one apply a symbolic language, an already existing symbolic architectural language
Làm thế nào người ta có thể áp dung một ngôn ngữ kí hiệu, môn ngôn ngữ kiến trúc đã sẵn có mà
that was developed over thousands of years as an expression of the heavy compressive
đã được phát triển qua hàng ngàn năm như
forces in masonry, to lightweight
forces in masonry, to lightweight
and thin structures
và cấu trúc mỏng
of metal and glass?
của kim loại và kính
How does one achieve the requisite monumentality and profundity with such flimsy materials?
How does one achieve the requisite monumentality and profundity with such flimsy materials?
This was the primary problem for the architects of the 20th century.
Đây là vấn đề quan trọng  đối với các kiến trúc sư thê kỉ 20.